### **Umesh Deshmukh**

Cell: +91 9850994518 • Email: umesh.deshmukh@cognizant.com

Having over 20 years of experience including delivery management, account management, project management, analysis, design, development and testing. Certified Scrum Master and more than 3 years of experience in following Agile scrum. Managed onsite and offshore software projects.

### CORE COMPETENCIES

- · Delivery Management · Project Management · Scrum Master · Can-do Attitude
- · Strong Analytical Skills · Good Interpersonal & Communication skills · People Management

#### **TECHNICAL BACKGROUND AND SKILLS**

ASP.Net, VB.Net, ADO.Net, ASP, PHP, VBScript, JavaScript, HTML, IIS, Apache, Linux, Windows, MS SQL Server 2000 and MySQL

#### **EDUCATION**

Masters in Computer Management, Pune University, 1999 Bachelor of Computer Science, Pune University, 1995

# CERTIFICATION

Certified Scrum Master
UiPath

# Career Highlights

## Cognizant Technology Solutions, Pune, 2007 till date

Ø Conducted Recathon to accelerate delivery of reconciliations and completed 7 out of 12 reconciliations

Ø As a Software Product Specialist, responsible for creating PoCs, demoing the product to Customers

Ø Played role as Offshore Program Manager for a program having revenue of around USD 4 Million for a UK Customer and maintained profitability around 47%

Ø Played role of Project Manager and won runner-up award as Global Project of the Year 2016 in Digital Systems & technology category (Small) & awarded as Ace team by Customer

Ø As a Scrum Master, involved in setting up and managing distributed Scrum

Ø Won Star award for contribution to delivery and for contribution to innovation

Ø Managed End-to-end delivery which includes resourcing, budgeting, invoicing of about 30+ associates

## Manas Solutions Pvt Ltd, Pune, 2000 till 2007

ø Worked only for Japanese clients for 7 years (both at Onsite & Offshore)

ø Tech Lead for various ASP & PHP projects

ø Played key role in defining the processes for ISO 9001:2000 standards in the organization

~ Please refer to annexure for details on projects ~

#### ~ ANNEXURE ~

### **Cognizant Technology Solutions (latest 5 projects)**

**Title:** GRS Migration

Role: Program Lead

**Tenure**: Sep-2019 till date

**Technologies**: Python, Informatica, CTC, Oracle

**Description**: A leading Bank needed to migrate the Reconciliation platform from Intellimatch to CTC (Clarety transaction Control). The main objective behind this migration was reduce time to market, achieve material savings in cost of the service across GRS Operations & IT. There were around 225+ reconciliations in scope (across APAC, EMEA, Swiss & America regions) for this program. Till Sep-2020, we have been able to deliver around 77+ reconciliation on new platform.

### Responsibilities:

- · Planning & Managing the regional reconciliation migration
- Identifying and highlighting risks in the program proactively
- · Tracking and reporting the status of the program
- Working with different teams to ensure Infrastructure availability
- · Resolve the dependencies across teams
- Ensuring 100% Process adherence
- · Finding ways to accelerate the deliverables

**Achievements:** Conducted Recathon across EMEA & APAC region to accelerate the deliverables. Completed 7 out of 12 recs within span of 2 weeks

**Title:** Digital Intake Framework

**Role**: Software Product Specialist

Tenure: Oct-2017 till date

Technologies: Java J2EE, MongoDB, Tesseract, Python OpenCV, AWS, AngularJS, Katalon

Studio

**Description**: DIF offers 3 components OCR, Classification and Extraction. OCR component reads an image and its metadata and stores in MongoDB. Classification component categorizes documents using few keywords. Extraction component is used to extract values for specified keyword.

### Responsibilities:

- Demoing DIF to various clients
- Develop PoC for various customers
- Writing Classification Rules for various documents
- · Writing Extraction rules (using Regex) for various documents
- Testing new features developed
- Suggesting changes from usability perspective
- Writing automated test cases using Katalon Studio

**Title:** Product Information Management

**Role**: Offshore Program Manager

Tenure: Jan-2017 till Sep-2017

Technologies: STEP, Mulesoft, AWS

**Description**: Products were not getting listed on their Website and hence was not sold due to insufficient metadata. To overcome this problem, client decided to use products named as STEP (by Stibo) and DAM (by Delaware). Project scope included installation & configuration of the product and integration of the product with existing systems.

# Responsibilities:

- · Planning & Managing the program within given budget & time
- · Identifying and highlighting risks in the program proactively
- · Tracking and reporting the status of the program
- Coordination with Onsite Program Manager
- Resourcing

**Title:** Product re-platforming

Role: Scrum Master & Project Manager

**Tenure**: Jun-2016 till Dec-2016

**Technologies**: TFS, Visual Studio .NET 2012, .NET Framework 4.5, C#, Mongo DB, Azure

**Description**: Product Platform is responsible for maintaining Product Catalog information that are to be sold on Site. Earlier, product information was maintained in legacy monolith application with SQL Database at the back end. As a part of re-platforming, this application is split into multiple micro-services based pipelines with Microsoft Azure as a platform. These micro-services are developed with Azure Service Fabric and are communicating with each other using Azure Service Bus. To support high traffic, MongoDB and Cosmos DB are used to store data. Teams followed automated testing and deployment activities. All these micro-services are governed by automated alerting and monitoring tools to proactively report a problem for quicker resolution in Production environment.

### Responsibilities:

- · Conducting Scrum ceremonies
- · Remove impediments of the team & enable team to perform at the best
- Status reporting, Release Planning
- · Coordination with Onsite Release Manager

Achievements: Runner-up: Global Project of the year 2016 in Digital Systems & Technology (Small)

Cognizant project team got Ace Team award by Client

**Title:** Website Maintenance

Role: Scrum Master

Tenure: Aug-2012 till May-2016

Technologies: TFS, Visual Studio .NET 2012, .NET Framework 4.5, C#, Mongo DB, Azure

**Description**: Client had Website, which was developed in 2004 using C# & VB.NET. Scrum Master of one of the first 2 teams with which the account was started. Involved in Onsite KT, adopting Scrum and Client specific processes. Work involved small enhancements to Website.

### Responsibilities:

- Ensuring smooth KT
- Reverse KT
- · Adopting Client Scrum processes
- · Conducting Scrum Ceremonies
- · Remove impediments of the team & enable team to perform at the best
- · Support and drive process improvement initiatives
- · Attending Scrum of Scrums with Client
- · Improve velocity
- · Resourcing, Invoicing
- · Creation of smaller utilities to enhance productivity

# **Summary of Cognizant projects & roles (prior to Aug-2011)**

- Key member at Onsite in assessment phase (around 3 months) of a Sales & Marketing data warehouse for a leading Pharmaceutical company in Japan. Post assessment, helped in winning the first project, worked as Onsite Lead for around 6 months, and then continued working from Offshore for around one and half year. Responsible for understanding business domain, coordination with Offshore team for knowledge sharing, drive and contribute to knowledge sharing, helping BD team to prepare proposal.
- · Played role of Onsite Project Manager for another leading Pharmaceutical company in Japan for disposition of various applications since the site was being closed. Worked with third party vendor as well during the 8-month project. Responsible for liaising with Customer and handle the requirements, queries, tracking and reporting project progress to the customer, identify, assess and mitigate risks, provide work direction and guidance to the team
- Onsite Coordinator for a first time client (leading Financial Institution in Japan). Responsible for driving and participating in requirements gathering meetings, passing on the requirements to Offshore, System design, status reporting, schedule & tracking project activities

- · Mainly worked in Developer & Tech lead role on technologies like ASP, PHP, ASP.NET
- Worked with clients like NTT Data, Japan Railways, ING Japan
- · Was deputed to Onsite, Tokyo, Japan from Oct 2002 till Jan 2003